<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A glasse for gamesters and namelie for suche as delight in cards &amp; dise: wherein thei maie see not onely the vanitie, but also the vilenesse of those plaies plainly discouered and ouerthrowen by the word of God. Written by T.W.</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838825</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1161:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A glasse for gamesters and namelie for suche as delight in cards &amp; dise: wherein thei maie see not onely the vanitie, but also the vilenesse of those plaies plainly discouered and ouerthrowen by the word of God. Written by T.W.</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Kyngston, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.W. = Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-d e⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print blurred and show-through; some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gambling --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3214:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3214:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A GLASSE for Gameſters: <hi>and namelie for ſuche as</hi>
               </hi> delight in Cards &amp; Diſe: wherein thei maie ſee not onely the vanitie, but alſo the vileneſſe of thoſe plaies plainly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen by the word of God. Written by <hi>T.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprinted at London by Ihon Kyngston, for Thomas Man. 1581.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3214:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3214:2"/>
            <head>¶ A Glaſse for Gameſters.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The first Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eyng that the lewſeneſſe and blindneſſe of this our age, either of ignoraunce perceiueth not, or of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice will not vnderſtande, what greate euill enſueth, by the plaie of Cardes and Diſe, and other games of lotte, fortune, or chaunce (as men vſe to call them) I haue thought good to putt doune, and by writyng breefly to ſhewe, the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and reaſons which maie make the inconueniences hereof to bee ſenſiblie perceiued, yea ſeene as it were with the eye, and touched with the hand. And although I knowe (by the little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whiche God hath giuen me) that in theſe euill daies of the worlde (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all maner of vngodlineſſe doeth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
<pb facs="tcp:3214:3"/> abound) there is greate ſtore of mockers and contemners of God and good thynges, men altogether inflamed and ſette on fire, to run after their owne pleaſures, yea and that euen in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Chriſtian congregation, who peraduenture for all this, will not leaue their vanitie, and in reſpect of whom, all the trauaile, that I now take, ſhalbe but labor loſte:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaiah. 55.11.</note> yet becauſe I am aſſured by the woorde of God, that the truthe ſhall neuer be vttered in vaine, and becauſe I hope, that euen in theſe wicked daies there are ſome (though the number bee but ſmall) with whom good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell ſhall preuaile (when thei ſhall ſee the euill thei haue doen) to drawe them backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniences, and diſorder. I haue for their ſakes the more willingly atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted this matter. For notablie in deede, and full of greate comforte, bothe in the inſtructor, and the partie inſtructed, is this ſaiyng of the holie ghoſt:<note place="margin">Prouerb. 9.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to the wiſe, &amp; he will be the wiſer: teach the righteous man, and he will increaſe in learnyng.</hi> But terrible
<pb facs="tcp:3214:3"/> to the one, and full of heauineſſe to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are theſe ſaiynges:<note place="margin">Prouer. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Fooles deſpiſe wiſedome and inſtruction.</hi> And again. <hi>Though thou ſhouldeſt braie a foole in a Morter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouer. 27.22</note> 
                  <hi>emong Wheate braied with a Peſtell, yet will not his fooliſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, depart from hym.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The ſeconde Chapter.</head>
               <p>HEre in the beginning, I will put doune the thinges I purpoſe to deale withall, &amp; the order, whiche I minde to obſerue in handelyng of the ſame. As, firſt, whether a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maie plaie, yea or no? Secondlie, whether it be lawfull, to plaie at any game for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? Thirdly, I wil name thoſe Games whiche I take to be vnlawfull. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I will make it plaine, by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Scripture, of auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, generall Councelles, the Ciuill and Canon Lawe, yea and of the Pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims themſelues, that theſe plaies of chaunce and fortune, and namely them of Diſe and Cardes (for my purpoſe is
<pb facs="tcp:3214:4"/> ſpeciallie to touche them) are not tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, nor to bee vſed of them, whiche make profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſtianitie. Laſtlie, I will aunſwere, in as fewe wordes, as I can, the obiections and reaſons of ſuch men, as maintaine theſe Plaies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The third Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſte matter, whiche I am to intreate of, is a queſtion: and that is, whether a Chriſtian man maie plaie, at any maner of game, yea or no? Whiche I thinke meete to be handeled, becauſe there is in theſe daies emongeſt vs, not onely diuerſitie, but contrarietie of iudgementes touchyng this matter.<note place="margin">Libertines, Atheiſtes, and carnall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsers.</note> For the greateſt number (plaie it ſelf beyng a thing, wherein the fleſhe verie muche delighteth) thinke that thei maie lawfullie plaie at all ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: an opinion ſurely verie deteſtable, and to be ſhunned of all true Chriſtians. An other ſorte there are,<note place="margin">Anabaptiſtes and others.</note> who ſeeyng the euill, that enſueth of ſome games vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, holde it therefore vnlawfull to
<pb facs="tcp:3214:4"/> play at any game: a iudgement, thought not ſounde, and therefore to be auoided, yet nothing ſo daungerous, as the other. Becauſe this (though ouer muche and more in deede then reaſon would) bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the fleſhe, a thing whiche ſtandeth in neede of very muche taming and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duyng, whereas the other loſeth the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; openeth not a window onely, but a broad gate, to many greate miſchiefes and greeuous inconueniences. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian therefore is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, how he may eſcape theſe twoo greate gulfes, and how he maie ſo behaue hym ſelf, that in this behalfe he bee no ſclaunder, to that holie profeſſion, wherein God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hym. I, for myne owne parte (and yet in all that I write, I willinglie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte my ſelf, and my iudgement to the cenſure of Gods Church) am neither ſo leuſe, as the firſte ſorte, nor ſo rigorous or ſcrupulous as the other: but am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (of whiche minde alſo ſainct <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſeemeth to be) that it is the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a wiſe, or godlie man,<note place="margin">Auguſtin. libr. 2. de Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſica. cap. 14.</note> ſometymes ſo to recreate hym ſelf, by lawfull exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:5"/> that he maie be able to endure, and holde out, in the labour of thoſe thinges, whiche he hath attempted and begunne: and doe affirme, that it is good to haue (as it were) a breathyng tyme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes he maie returne more chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to his ordinarie trauaile and labour. Wee ſee, that the holie ſcripture (which is the onelie rule, to trie out good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill) bothe maketh mention of plaiyng, and permitteth the ſame to Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Zechariah. 8.5</note>In the Prophet <hi>Zechariah,</hi> wée haue theſe woordes. <hi>And the ſtreates of the Citie ſhall bee full of boies and girles, plaiyng in the ſtreates thereof.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Corint. 10.31</note> Alſo, when ſainct <hi>Paule</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Whether ye eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer ye doe, doe all to the glorie of God:</hi> wee maie vnderſtande this woorde, <hi>whatſoeuer,</hi> to comprehende any godlie and honeſt recreation: whiche without doubte is as lawfull for vs, by reaſon of the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and weakeneſſe of our Nature, as is drinke, meate, ſlepe, or any other thing, when we haue neede thereof. And as we maie by our Sauiour Chriſtes wordes
<pb facs="tcp:3214:5"/> in S. <hi>Marke</hi> plainly gather this poinct:<note place="margin">Marke. 2.27.</note> to witte: <hi>That the Sabbath was made for man and his vſe,</hi> and all to this ende, that it might bee referred to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, his owne good, and the benefite and profite of others. So I ſuppoſe, that a man maie ſafelie, and without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to the truthe conclude, that honeſt and lawfull recreation, hath been inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for manne and for his healthes ſake, and the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his life (I meane not, that plaie can prolong mannes life,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.5.</note> for all our daies are numbred, ſo that we cannot paſſe them) in whiche while wee are, we haue (no doubt) wonderfull, and vnſpeakable occaſions offered vs, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie and holilie to ſerue the Lorde our God. Whiche I thinke to bee one of the cheefeſt cauſes, why GOD hath placed men in this worlde, and one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt reaſons whiche moued <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 30 9. Iſaiah. 38.3.1</note> 
                  <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> and others, to deſire of the Lorde, long life, and continuaunce vppon the yearth. I confeſſe in deede, that all and euery one of our actions, ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the glorie of God, and the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:3214:6"/> and profite of our neighbours.</p>
               <p>Neither doubt I, but that, if wee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace our ſelues honeſtly and godlie, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by indeuouring to mainteine (as muche as in vs lieth) our ſtrength, to vpholde healthe, to repaire our forces, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce in ſome exerciſes, a little as it were decaied, to refreſhe our Spirites, dulled or ouerwhelmed with ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours or ſtudies: and all this wee doe to this ende, that wee maie afterwardes, when our duetie requireth, more ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and chearfully giue our ſelues ouer to that callyng, wherein it hath pleaſed God to ſette vs, and might bee thereby made the more fitte and better able to performe the ſame: I doubte not I ſaie but that in the ende, this ſhall redounde bothe to the glory of God, whom by this meane, wee ſerue more readilie: and to the good of our neighbours, whom, wee beeyng freſhe and well diſpoſed thereto, maie more eaſelie and commodiouſlie helpe, accordyng to ſuche abilitie, as the Lorde hath giuen vs.</p>
               <p>The nature and ſpirite of man, maie
<pb facs="tcp:3214:6"/> in my iudgement, be aptly compared to a Bowe, which how ſtrong ſoeuer it be, if it bee alwaies kept bent, is not onelie in daunger of marring: but by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes becommeth, bothe verie weake, and afterwardes beeyng drawen, is eaſelie broken: but if it be bent, for the time that a man vſeth to ſhoote in the ſame, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes vnbent, ſette vp and kept in good order, it is preſerued and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth a long while. No man I thinke, hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer denied, but that it is lawfull and fitt for a Chriſtian, if he be ſicke, to vſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie and godlie meanes for the recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of health. And why I pray you ſhould it bee leſſe lawfull to vſe lawfull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meanes, for the continuaunce and preſeruation of healthe? The vſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meanes is not vnlawfull, but truſt in them is forbidden. To vſe them, with truſt in them, is to ſhutt God out of the doores, and place his creatures in his ſteede. On the other ſide, to neglecte or refuſe them, whiche God hath ordeined, is to tempt God, and therfore we ought warely to ſhunne, and auoide bothe theſe
<pb facs="tcp:3214:7"/> extremities. Verely in my iudgement, this ſhould be too greate a crueltie in no wiſe to graunt, that a nature ouermuche wearied with ſtudie, or a manne ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought with trauaile, might not or ſhould not recreate hym ſelf. And on the other ſide, this were too greate a leuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to let hym vſe at all tymes, lawfull recreation, or at any other tyme vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I take plaie at honeſt and lawfull games, to be a thing allowable, and lawfull, and to bee of the number of thoſe thinges, whiche are lefte in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie:<note place="margin">Galath. 5.13.</note> whiche libertie wee muſte not abuſe, as an occaſion vnto the fleſhe, but accordyng to ſuche rules, as GOD hath lefte for the lawfull vſe of the ſame in his holie worde. Wherefore I forbid not, neither doe I condemne all maner of plaie: yea, I thinke it not euill, that ſometymes a Chriſtian man plaie and refreſhe hym ſelf. Prouided alwaie, that ſuche recreation and delight, bee in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges lawfull and honeſt, &amp; that alſo with moderation or meaſure. For it is not meete, that men ſhould ſpende at plaie
<pb facs="tcp:3214:7"/> (though the plaie it ſelf be neuer ſo law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) either thoſe thinges, or that tyme, whiche God hath allotted hym, to other endes and purpoſes. For God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him goodes for the mainteinance of him ſelf and his familie, and the releeuyng of thoſe, whiche want neceſſarie ſuccour and maintenaunce. The Lorde hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appoincted hym a tyme, whiche he ought to ſpende, in the faithfull diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng of that office, whiche the Lorde hath laied vpon hym. So that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall thus exceſſiuelie and vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, waſte theſe good thinges (yea I ſaie, though it were at lawfull games) ſhalbe ſubiecte to Gods heauie iudgemente, for the miſerable and wicked abuſyng of thoſe his good giftes: and ſhall no doubt (vnleſſe ſpéedy and vnfeined repentance enſue) feele the hande of God vpon him, for his ſynne and tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thus muche for the aunſweryng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which think it not lawfull to play at any game: with ſomewhat alſo touching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thinke it lawfull to plaie at all games. But theſe men ſhalbe more particularly
<pb facs="tcp:3214:8"/> and fullie aunſwered, in the diſcourſe of this treatie, and namely in the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ouchyng the ſeconde poinct, I feare not to affirme, that it is vnlawfull to plaie for money, to winne it, and purſe it vppe when it is wonne, that is to ſaie, either for a man to loſe his owne money, or to winne an other mans, and ſo to make gaine of the ſame. As concernyng bothe their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, that is, the winner and the loſer, I ſaie generally, that thei both doe euill in this, in turnyng vpſide doune the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of plaie, and the ende, for whiche plaie and gamenyng was deuiſed. For whereas plaie was appointed in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnyng, onely for the exerciſe of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or recreation of the ſpirit, theſe men omittyng thoſe endes, make it a meane to gaine or get money by, and ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and alter the nature of recreation, into a kinde of vnhoneſt and vnlawfull game, whiche thyng Chriſtians (bee it little or
<pb facs="tcp:3214:8"/> be it much) are plainely forbidden by the worde of God. And as touching the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that loſeth, he is depriued of that (yea though it bee but a little) whiche either might doe good in his familie, or profite other the needie members of Chriſt: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that whiche followeth vpon this lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as diſquietnes of minde at the leaſt, if not curſing, ſweareyng, quarellyng and ſuche other like, whiche make the matter on his ſide, and in reſpect of hym much more intollerable: Adde to al this, what wiſedome doeth it argue to bee in that man, who when he hath the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a thyng in his owne handes, will by Cardes, Diſe, and ſuch other vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful exerciſes, make triall whether it ſhal be his owne? And if the looſer fall into theſe inconueniences, ſo that on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, it is not lawfull for him to plaie for money, by what right or reaſon ſhall we thinke, it maie be lawfull in the winner. That which he getteth at plaie, he muſt get either by right or by wrong, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene theſe twoo, there is very little or no meane at al: If he get it wrongfully,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:9"/> I thinke all the worlde will condemne hym therefore: becauſe that though the worlde delight in wrongfull dealing, yet ſuche is the might and power of truthe, (and that euen in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche doe wrong them ſelues) that it maketh them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that vice in others, wherewith they them ſelues bee defiled and infected. If thei will ſaie, thei get it rightfully, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhewe by what lawe. This ſaiyng of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Lawier, <hi>Id poſſumus quod iure poſſumus, wee maie dooe that onely which by lawe we may do,</hi> is (hauing a godly interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) a very good ſaiyng. Sure I am, that all the Gameſters in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, if thei ſhould laie their heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhal neuer be able to proue, either by the lawe of God, or by mans lawe, that plaie was at any tyme receiued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, to be (as it were) a certain kinde of Marchandize, traffick, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainyng awaie of our goodes, or a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes whereby to get other mens gooddes. Amongſt al the lawes of men, whiche haue at large ſette out all honeſt meanes, rightly to come by, and lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3214:9"/> to poſſeſſe the goods of an other, the ciuill Lawe is very excellent, and hath moſte largely and carefully put doune the ſame, and yet amongſt all the honeſt meanes there declared, plaie is not ſo muche as recited or reckoned vp, naye cannot bee compriſed, either directly or indirectly, vnder any terme there expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. There is mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of bargaines of ſale, of hiryng of others thynges, of promiſing to leaue a thing better then a man findeth it, and ſuche like, by whiche wee maie iuſtly haue and poſſeſſe that, whiche is an others, but of lawfull poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyng an other mans goods gotten by plaie, not ſo muche as one worde, title or iotte, tendyng to that ende. So that (ſeeyng neither in God his lawe, nor mans, any thing is found for it) we may well inferre, that whoſoeuer taketh and withholdeth the money of an other, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng wonne it at plaie, withholdeth it without any lawfull cauſe, and therfore hath it with an euill conſcience. And if this ſhould be permitted, ſe what would inſue thereupon: men ſhould bring in an
<pb facs="tcp:3214:10"/> vnſatiable couetouſneſſe, in the place of the recreation of the mynde, and an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to beguile one an other, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteede of delightyng and reioyſing the ſpirite, whiche is ſo farre of from refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng either of the parties which plaie, that it is a continuall trouble and boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng in them, one while hauyng a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die deſire to winne and gaine that which is an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and an other while vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and moued, that he ſhall leeſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe his owne. And though there were neuer ſo many cuſtomes, politick lawes, euill vſes, and corruptions of maners, ſet againſte this truthe, that here I put doune (albeit for my parte I knowe no lawe or cuſtome, that ſaieth otherwiſe then I ſaie here) yet durſt I boldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouche, that to winne money at plaie, and to purſe it vp, is vtterly intollerable and vnlawfull, yea that it is plainely and directly, againſt this laſt commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſeconde Table:<note place="margin">Exod. 20.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet:</hi> for tell me (I praie you) who is he among al the plaiers in the world, that hath not this greedie deſire in hym,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:10"/> rather to winne an other mans, then to leeſe his owne, though he plaie for neuer ſo little or ſmall a ſomme? And herein I am not alone, for amongſte the Lawes and ſtatutes of Geneua (a Citie for the Godlines there practiſed,<note place="margin">The lawes of Geneua. folio 70. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lin. 8 Alſo fol. 80. pag. 1. lin. 8.</note> worthie of all men to be reuerenced) it is decreed that no man plaie at any maner of game for money, whoſoeuer ſhall doe otherwiſe, ſhall forfeite thréeſcore ſhillinges in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and abide three daies in priſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. That not able man <hi>Peter Martir,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Peter Martir in cap 14. lib. Iudicum. fol. 148. pag 2. lin. 44. &amp;c.</note> in his Commentaries vpon the Iudges, both aunſweareth an obiection, that men vſe to make for their defence in this behalf, and plainly declareth his mynde herein. His wordes are theſe: But ſome ſay, thei delight not in plaie, except thei plaie for money. But I will demaunde of them, to what vſe thei intende to beſtowe that money? Peraduenture thei will ſaie, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a feaſte. Why not rather vppon the poore? But I ſaie, it is much better and ſafer not to plaie for any money: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it maie be, that thou thy ſelf art not touched with couetouſnes, the other
<pb facs="tcp:3214:11"/> yet with whom thou plaieſt, is peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture touched: let the occaſions vnto euill be taken awaie, which otherwiſe are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many, whiche moue vnto euill, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hottomanus lib. 2. devſuris</note>
                  <hi>Maiſter Franciſcus Hottomanus,</hi> not onely a greate learned Lawier, but a Chriſtian Lawier, is of the ſame iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo, and teacheth, that by the very order and diſpoſition of the Ciuill lawe, gaine gotten at plaie, and purſed vp, is a thing forbidden, and iuſtly to be diſliked. Neither is <hi>Sainct Auguſtine</hi> farre from this mynde, who willeth that the money wonne at plaie, ſhould bee giuen to the poore: to the ende, that bothe the looſer ſhould be puniſhed, not hauyng againe, that whiche he loſt: and the winner alſo depriued of his hope, hauyng nothing of that, which he had euil gotten. Beſides, what reaſon is there I praie you, to turne that, whiche was founde out and deuiſed for mans recreation, into an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of couetouſneſſe and filthie gaine? What ſhewe of reaſon is there in this, that (there being ſo many poore as there are, in the Churche of God, and they to
<pb facs="tcp:3214:11"/> in ſuch greate miſerie &amp; neede) he which is called a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and brother of theſe poore, and acknowledgeth them for the members of Ieſus Chriſte, ſhould plaie and ſpende his money at his pleaſure, and that at vnlawful games, rather then to diſtribute it in almes, and giue it to his poore brethren,<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 58.7.</note> who in the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res are called his owne fleſhe? Cannot money (beyng of it ſelf the good gifte of God, be better imployed, then vnthrift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be conſumed at Cardes, Dice, and other vnlawfull games? If wee would looke well about vs, we ſhould ſee, that with it, many poore children might bee prouided for, and inſtructed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and religion, and ſo become after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde profitable members in the church or common wealth: we ſhall finde many ſicke and weake ones, which haue neede to be relieued, and many priſoners and exiles, that ought to be comforted: to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto whom if we bee able, rather then waſte it at vnlawfull games, our dueties preſcribed vnto vs in the worde of GOD, doe very ſtraightly binde vs.
<pb facs="tcp:3214:12"/> What a greefe and horror of conſcience, wilbe vnto vs one daie, though now we conſider not of it, when wee ſhall buye this our pleaſure ſo deare? Were it not better for vs,<note place="margin">Luke. 16.9.</note> to followe Chriſtes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and to make vs frendes with our money, not thoſe whiche winne it from vs in plaie (for neither doeth our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſte meane it of ſuche, neither ſhall thei ſtande vs in any ſteede at that daie, vnleſſe it be to be witneſſes of our ſynnes,<note place="margin">Prouer. 19.17.28.27.</note> and to accuſe vs) but the Godly poore, vppon whom, looke whatſoeuer we beſtowe, we ſhall bee ſure to haue it plentifully, with greate profite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe reſtored vnto vs again, in the daie of that great iudgement of God.<note place="margin">Augu tom. 8. colum. 116<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. d.</note> 
                  <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> will not haue a faithfull man, to giue his money to a Iuggler, or Stage plaier, although that by his trauaile and pleaſure, wee receiue ſome pleaſure: muche leſſe me thinketh ſhould he ſuffer vs,<note place="margin">Idem tom. 9. colum. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. a.</note> to giue our money vnto a gameſter, whiche plaieth with vs, and whom we our ſelues for our parte make merie, as well as he maketh vs merie? This is
<pb facs="tcp:3214:12"/> then my concluſion, that the plaiyng for money, and the purſyng of it vp, when it is obtained and gotten in plaie is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, bothe in reſpecte of the thyng it ſelf (becauſe it taketh awaie the end, why plaiyng was ordained): and alſo of the perſones, becauſe the loſer is vniuſtlie diſpoſſeſſed of his owne, &amp; the other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfullie poſſeſſed in that, whiche is an other mans. Neither will I here make any diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Plaies or Games. For whether the Game it ſelf be good or euil tollerated or forbidden, it ſkilleth not in this behalfe. And yet I muſte confeſſe, that it is a greater euill, to winne it at vnlawfull games, then otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The v. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are now to declare, whiche be plaies prohibited &amp; vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Touchyng whiche, firſt I affirme, that all ſuche plaies as the lawe and cuſtome of the Countrie wherein a man doeth liue, forbiddeth, are to be held as vnlawfull, but yet with this conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3214:13"/> that thoſe lawes thus forbiddyng ſuche plaies, be grounded vppon ſome honeſte and holy conſiderations: otherwiſe if the Magiſtrate forbid ſuch plaies, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians maie lawfully vſe, I thinke, that if the Chriſtian vſe thoſe games forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, with certaine Godly conditions, he doeth not offende. My meanyng is this, that in ſuch caſes, men are to take heede, that thei doe nothing openly, to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like contempt of the order taken by the Magiſtrate, whom God hath placed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: neither priuately in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thoſe, whiche are ſcrupulous in conſcience. Touchyng the obſeruation, of all whatſoeuer poſitiue Lawes of Princes, leaſt that by this doyng, they ſhould by their examples, make others to neglect publike orders, and draw vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them the wrath of the prince (which is as a meſſenger of death,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 19.12 20.2. 16.14.</note> and like the roryng of a Lion) for their tranſgreſſion of his Lawe, and greeue or trouble the myndes of the weake. For plaie beyng as I ſaied before, a thyng allowable or lawfull, wee are therein to conſider not
<pb facs="tcp:3214:13"/> onely what we maie doe, but alſo, what ſhall bee profitable for vs to doe:<note place="margin">1. Corin. 10.23</note> and to looke not to our ſelues alone,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.21.</note> but with all to haue an eye to this, that we greeue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſciences of the weake. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſaie, that al thoſe plaies are vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in which there are alurementes and prouocations (whether it be by wordes, deedes, countenances, or any other waie whatſoeuer either ſecrete or open) to wantoneſſe, diſſolutenes, or diſhoneſtie, be it I ſaie, either in effect, or be it onely in wordes and appearaunce. Touchyng the deedes, I thinke there are but fewe ſo wicked that will denie it. Touchyng the countenaunce, wordes, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, perhappes thei will make ſome ſtaie, and ſaie that it cannot be. To aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere whom, though I might alledge, many good and ſounde reaſons, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy Scripture is that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt ſtoppe the mouthes of al ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of the truthe, I will make that alone, my foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ground worke, touchyng this matter. For countenance we ſee what our Sauiour ſaieth. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:3214:14"/> looketh vpon a woman to luſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her,<note place="margin">Math. 5.28.</note> hath committed adulterie with her alreadie in his harte. The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherof made Dauid to praie to the Lorde,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.37.</note> to turne awaie his eyes from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding vanitie. And as for wordes our Sauiour alſo telleth vs,<note place="margin">Math. 12.36.</note> that of euery idle woorde that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue account thereof at the daie of Iudgement:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 141.3.</note> the conſideration whereof made Dauid in an other place to praie, and ſaie: Set a watche, O Lorde before my mouthe, and keepe the doore of my lippes. And as for appearaunce, the holy Ghoſte is ſo preciſe therein, that by the mouth of the Apoſtle Sainct Paule,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.22.</note> he commaundeth vs to abſtaine from all outwarde ſhewe and appearaunce of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. By whiche we gather, that all theſe filthie plaies of daunſinges, maſkinges, mummynges, and other the like, ſhould be baniſhed and driuen farre awaie, from the companie of Chriſtians, becauſe thei bee not onely little entraunces, or ſmall beginnynges to muche wickedneſſe, but fierbrandes, or rather in deede, greate
<pb facs="tcp:3214:14"/> flames of villanous and ſecrete whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and many other vices: A thirde ſorte of plaies there is, whiche be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and theſe in one generall terme, I call the games of chaunce. I call theſe games, or plaies of chaunce, in whiche men are directed, rather by chaunce, to obtaine the game and victorie, at ſuche a plaie, then by cunnyng and induſtrie. Thei of old tyme were wont alſo, to call theſe games, the plaies of chaunce or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and thei did define them after this maner. Plaie of Chaunce or hazard, is all maner of plaie, where the aduenture and euent of chaunce, beyng as it were hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vnknowne, the victorie by the ſame chaunce, is giuen and brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that winneth. There was of theſe games many kinde of ſortes, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by <hi>Iulius Pollux,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Onomaſticon lib 8. cap. vlt.</note> all whiche the men of olde tyme, did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſe vnder this word <hi>Deca,</hi> as the Frenchmen at this daie doe the ſame, vnder the name of Cardes, and Diſe: againſt whiche, as I mynde chiefly to ſpeake in this treatie: ſo here I put doune, that euen for this reaſon,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:15"/> becauſe thei be games of chaunce or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (as we call it) that therefore thei be not onely daungerous, but alſo intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and altogether vnlawfull. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will not be thought to be alone, I thinke it not amiſſe here to put doune <hi>Peter Martirs</hi> iudgement touchyng this matter.<note place="margin">Petrus Martir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n 14. lib. Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um. fol. 148. pag. 1. lin. 36.</note> We muſt decree ſaieth he (that ſuche plaies, ought not to bee ſuffred, which are couered by chaunce and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that in them goods and money are indaungered, becauſe it belongeth to the publike wealth, to ſée that thinges be rightly gouerned, and GOD giueth goods to bee ſpent to good vſes: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by it ſpryng oftentymes horrible blaſphemies, and robbing of our fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and a couetous deſire of other mennes goods, is ſtirred vp, beſides the greate loſſe of tyme. If any man will denie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee games of chaunce, that is eaſely anſweared. For muſt not men take that whiche the Die caſt, or the Carde delt, giueth and bringeth. So that though we would gladly haue, either a better caſt at Diſe, or a better game at Cardes,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:15"/> yet wee cannot, but muſte content our ſelues with thai, whiche the Diſe, or the Cardes giue vs. Wherevpon it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that the victorie falleth, where it pleaſeth the Cardes and Diſe to giue it: of whiche mynde alſo, euen <hi>Tullie</hi> hym ſelf is, who writeth thus? What is lot or chaunce? Euen that in deede whiche it is, to throwe the Diſe, in whiche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, raſhneſſe and chaunce, not reaſon and counſaile preuaileth. Yea but ſome will ſaie, wee can ſo ſette the Cardes and the Diſe, that we can winne when wee liſt, and haue what game ſeemeth good to our ſelues: ſo that it is not by chaunce, but as pleaſeth vs. To whiche I ſaie, that though this might bee ſome peece of an aunſwere, to wit, that many times, the cunningeſt in that wickednes are deceiued, yet I ad that this is a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſynne, added vnto ſynne, not onely by vnlawfull games to ſpoyle men, of that whiche is their owne, but alſo by treacherie and deceipt to winne it from them. How much I praie you doth this differ from couſnage, forbidden by the
<pb facs="tcp:3214:16"/> lawe of our Lande? And how much doth couſnage differ from a certaine ſecrete kinde of theft, which is forbidden by the lawe of GOD?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xod. 20.15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pheſ. 4.25.</note> And how many are the places in holy Scripture, by which ſuch craftie and deceiueable dealinges be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? Beſides that therevpon inſueth commonly, braulynges, quarelynges, fightynges, blowes, yea many tymes murther. But more of this particulare matter of Cardes and Diſe, in the next Chapter followyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The ſixt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to order before ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, put doune profes, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declaryng the vnlawfulnes of theſe games of Diſe &amp; Cardes. And firſt to beginne with the ſcriptures and reaſons annexed thereunto. I take theſe games of Diſe and Cardes, beyng as I ſaied before, games of lot, hazard, or chaunce, to bee ſtatly againſte the thirde commaundement,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> thou ſhalte not take
<pb facs="tcp:3214:16"/> the name of the Lorde thy God in vaine. The reaſon that leadeth me thereunto is this. Lot, or chaunce (as we call it) is one of the principall teſtimonies of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God,<note place="margin">Prou. 16.33.</note> becauſe it is ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned immediatly, by his hand and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and was neuer ordeined of God for any thyng, but for matters of greate weight, and neuer vſed amongeſt the Godly,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.5.6.</note> but in cauſes of greate impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, as in partyng of goods,<note place="margin">Nomb. 26.55.</note> diuidyng of landes, electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Magiſtrates, choiſe of Miniſters, and ſuch like thynges,<note place="margin">Samu. 10.20.21</note> and was appoincted to take awaie,<note place="margin">Actes. 1.26.</note> all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of heate, in wordes, and quarelles, and corruptions in ſpeache. Now for vs to take that, which God hath appointed to ſo greate and holy vſes onely, and to applie it, to ſerue our fonde affections, in euery light trifle, &amp; caſe of no weight, what is it, but to treade vnder foote, the ordinaunce and inſtitution of God, and ſo conſequently, to bee tranſgreſſors of that thirde Commaundement. Beſides that, it ſeemeth to bee a maner of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of God, when wee knowe, that he
<pb facs="tcp:3214:17"/> will not haue this vſed, but in matters of greate weight and importaunce, and yet wee will vſe it, in thynges of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, as though we would make God, a ſeruaunt of our pleaſures, laughters and delightes, and would knowe, whether he haue any care thereof, then the which, what can bee more ſtraunge to vtter, or fearefull to thinke?<note place="margin">Epheſi. 5.16.</note> Secondly, the ſpirite of God commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs, to redeeme the tyme, that we haue loſte, by exerciſyng our ſelues in vaine, idle, and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinges, and to beſtowe that tyme, whiche we now haue, in good and holy thynges, and ſuch as in déede maie ſerue to edification and profite. The reaſon whiche the holy Ghoſt vſeth to moue vs thereunto, is this, for the daies are euill, as if he would ſay: the more corrupt, that the maners of this worlde are, ſo muche the more neede wee haue, to vſe all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to take all occaſions, and to ſet nothyng before vs, but the good, holie, and acceptable will of God. To whiche alſo we maie adde, according to the truth of Gods woorde, an other taken from
<pb facs="tcp:3214:17"/> the brittleneſſe and ſhortnes of our owne liues here in this worlde.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 90.3.4. &amp;c.</note> Wherevpon I inferre, that whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe God, to giue vs a tyme and occaſion to bee occupied, either in readyng, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng his holy worde, viſityng the poore, comfortyng the afflicted, or doyng ſuche like thynges, it muſte bee taken quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. For occaſion is balde behynde,<note place="margin">Galath. 6.10.</note> and there maie (becauſe many thynges fall betweene the Cuppe, and the vpper lippe) fall out ſome lette, whiche we our ſelues doe not forſee, and whiche maye turne vs awaie from doyng that good. Moreouer, we our ſelues are eaſely dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen by vanitie and vaine perſwaſions, either of our owne fleſhe, or of our fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, from ſuche godlie exerciſes, While we haue time therefore, let vs doe good. Is not this thinke you, a pretie redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng tyme, to ſpende it awaie in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, Cardyng, and ſuche other vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie exerciſes, as neither Gods woords, nor godlie men either allowe or like of? The holie Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 4.3.</note> by ſainct <hi>Peter</hi> telleth vs, <hi>that it ought to be ſufficient for vs,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:18"/> that we haue ſpent the time paſt of our life after the luſtes of the Gentiles, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in wantonneſſe, luſtes, &amp;c.</hi> Wee ſaie on the other ſide, no it is not enough we will ſpende yet a little more tyme in theſe wicked delightes and pleaſures. What is this els I praie you, but to lye ſlumbering, in the dead ſleepe of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our owne nature, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaied, to ſynne vpon preſumption? And beſides let vs knowe this, that this our pleaſure, will in the ende without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, be recompenſed with horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paine and puniſhment. Thirdly, this plaie of Cardes and Diſe, carrieth with it a manifeſt conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the Magiſtrate, who hath forbidden the ſame, vpon good and holy conſiderations: and is beſides an offence and greife of conſcience, not onely to the weake, but alſo to others, whiche be of greater ſtrength, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the manifolde miſchiefes, and daie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconueniences, inſuyng vpon ſuche Plaies, are caried into ſuche a godly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and deteſtation of the ſame, that thei cannot awaie at any hande, to beholde it
<pb facs="tcp:3214:18"/> or ſee it. But iolie fellowes will thinke, this maie be eaſely aunſwered thus: If thei liſt not to looke vppon it, thei maie abſent them ſelues. But to them I ſaie, firſt that offence riſeth not only by ſight, but alſo vpon the hearyng or knowyng of that to be doen, whiche is vnlawfull. Secondly, that thei declare themſelues, to be voide of that ſame godly and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpirite, whiche ought to bee in the children of God. I am ſure that <hi>Sainct Paule</hi> was of an other mynde, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of greater importaunce then plaie. For he ſaieth thus.<note place="margin">1. Corin. 8.13.</note> 
                  <hi>If meate offende my brother, I will eate no fleſhe while the worlde ſtandeth, that I may not offend my brother.</hi> There is no manne in the worlde I thinke ſo blinde, but he ſeeth that the vſe of meate, for the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the bodie, is very neceſſarie, and one of the ordinarie meanes, which God hath appoincted for the maintenaunce of mans life. And yet <hi>Paule</hi> had ſuch a loue to the brethren (makyng hymſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an example for vs to followe) that he would willingly forgoe, that neceſſarie
<pb facs="tcp:3214:19"/> nouriſhment, rather then greiue or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them. But theſe men will not leaue that, not onely whiche thei maie leaue, without hurte of their bodies and liues, but alſo whiche thei ought to leaue, for feare of diſpleaſing God. For my parte I cannot ſée, what this ſhould be els, but that ſo ſinnyng againſt the brethren, and woundyng the conſcience of the Godly, thei ſinne againſt Chriſte. But perhaps the vngodly runnyng forwarde in ſinne, will ſaie, that S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh there, of meates dedicated to Idols.<note place="margin">1. Corin 8.13.</note> I graunt that. What then? Therefore thei ſaie it ſerueth not againſt plaie at Cardes and Diſe. This is but a ſhifte, and ſheweth the corrupt nature of man, who will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies gather figge leaues to couer his nakedneſſe, and filthineſſe withall. For my owne parte, though I ſee no reaſon to the contrarie, why the vſe of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous meates, ſhould not be as tollerable and lawfull amongſt Chriſtians, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and wicked games, yet will I preſſe them with an other place, from whiche thei ſhall neuer bee able to ſhifte
<pb facs="tcp:3214:19"/> them ſelues, though they had the wyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of al men liuyng. In the Epiſtle to the Romaines the Apoſtle ſaieth thus. <hi>It is good neither to eate fleſhe, nor to drinke Wine, nor to dooe any thyng, whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or made weake.</hi> Their diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Idolatrous meates here, wil not ſerue the turne. For the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of any ſuche thing, but ſheweth that bothe the vſe of Chriſtian libertie, and all the life of a Chriſtian man, ought to be referred to this end, that we ſhould builde vp one another by good workes, in ſo muche, that wee ſhould holde that thyng, whiche of it ſelf is pure and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in reſpect that it offendeth our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vncleane and vnlawfull. Beſides theſe generall termes (of any thyng) doe take awaie from them, all cloake and colour of repliyng. So that, vnleſſe thei wil open their mouthes againſt heauen, thei muſt needes yeeld to this truth: the contempt of whiche ſhall bee greuouſly puniſhed, as maie plainly be gathered, by the wordes of Chriſte ſaiyng, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:3214:20"/> ſhall offende one of theſe little ones whiche beleue in me,<note place="margin">Math. 18.6.</note> it were better for hym, that a Milſtone were hanged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute his necke, and that he were drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the depth of the Sea.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this plaie of Diſe and Cardes, is appointed and vſed againſte the very nature of that, whiche we call in Latin <hi>Ludus,</hi> and in Engliſhe, Plaie: and therefore is a verie corruption of lawfull exerciſe, whiche God hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto vs, and a verie turnyng vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide doune of true and lawfull plaie. For all plaie is appointed for men, and vſed and receiued emongeſt them, for twoo endes onely: that is to ſaie, either for the exerciſe of the bodie, or for the recreation of the Spirite. And how I praie you, is the bodie exerciſed, when the Plaiers be idle, and doe nothyng in a maner, but ſit ſtill continually? Or how is the minde of man refreſhed, when there is nothing on bothe ſides, till the ende of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> game, but a weariſome toylyng of the minde, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes in feare to loſe, ſometymes glad when the Diſe and Cardes goe with it,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:20"/> ſometymes frettyng, when thei goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it? Beſides all this, the loſer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and chaffyng for his loſſe, the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alſo hauyng his greedie deſire ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, when he hath ill gotten and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that, whiche he couetouſlie deſired of an other mannes. Is not this I praie you, to nouriſhe in our boſomes, not ſparkes, but whole flames of iniquitie, the verie imbers and aſhes whereof, we ought to caſte from vs? Notable is that counſell of the Wiſeman,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 21.2</note> if wee would bee ruled by it. <hi>Flie from ſynne as from a Serpent: for if thou commeſt too nere it, it will bite thee: the teeth thereof are as the teeth of a Lion to ſlaie the ſoules of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftlie, and laſtlie, the inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (what ſaie I inconueniences) Naie, ſynnes and horrible ſynnes, whiche dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enſue vppon the vſe of theſe vnlawfull Games, make theſe maner of plaiyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnlawfull. What ſhould I reckon vp, the curſynges, ſwearinges, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlie blaſphemies of the name of God, together with the brawlynges, quarel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:21"/> and fightynges commolie vſed emong the Gameſters? Of whiche thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, though wee our ſelues had no expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience (but here I muſte ſaie, that theſe horrible wickedneſſes are ouer rife, and common emongeſt vs) yet the Ciuill lawe would ſette it out vnto vs: whiche dooeth confiſcate the place it ſelf, where men haue plaied at ſuche &amp; ſuche vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Games, as it were nothyng, that ſuche a place, by reaſon of the euill, that ordinarelie hath been there committed, is rather a fitte Stie for filthie Swine, then a meete houſe for any honeſt man, to dwell in afterward. Why ſhould I touche the greedie, and coueteous deſire of the plaiers, gapyng continuallie, and greedelie deſiryng, to gette that the one from the other, in the lawfull poſſeſſion whereof, the Lorde hath placed them? What neede I to ſpeake of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hypocriſie and deceipt vſed in theſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, whileſt many makyng choiſe with whom thei plaie, to beleeue thei haue a good Game, thei diſſemble and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite, as though thei had an ill Game,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:21"/> thereby alluryng the other to greater loſſes.</p>
               <p>To what ende ſhould I rehearſe (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng al men knowe it) the miſerable wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng of theſe good thynges, whiche the Lorde hath giuen vs, as tyme, money, and ſuche other like? All whiche thynges if thei be conſidered, bee manifeſtlie and directlie againſt the expreſſe woorde of God. I might alledge a greate number of other circumſtances and reaſons, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie apt and fitte, againſt this deteſtable plaie, but this that I haue hetherto ſaid, will I hope bee ſufficient for good men, and ſuche as will imbrace good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. Touchyng the other, as I thinke it will bee verie hard, yea, an impoſſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e matter, to make them leaue their vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (ſo is the pleaſure of ſynne rooted in their hartes) ſo I thinke that the godlie Magiſtrate ſhould take order, for the bridelyng of ſuche diſordered perſones, either by ſaiyng vppon them greate pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, and mercementes, or by harde and ſtraite impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or els by ſome other godlie and lawfull meane, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:3214:22"/> the Magiſtrate ſhall thinke meete to bée vſed. But here perhappes ſome will ſaie we can auoide theſe miſcheeus, therfore why ſhould wee not plaie at theſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes? I aunſwere, it maie bee ſo, that ſome menne maie in deede in their plaie forbeare al theſe wickedneſſes. But ſhal I tel you what I thinke? Surely I am perſwaded, that thei are as rare birdes vpon the yearth, as a blacke Swanne, or a white Rauen. Beſides, if I ſhould graunt, that men could vſe plaie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe miſchiefes, yet it would not followe, that plaiyng at Cardes &amp; Diſe were lawfull. For I haue before proued the vnlawfulnes of theſe games, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide declared, that whether the plaie it ſelf bee lawfull or vnlawfull, yet it is at no hande lawful, to plaie at the ſame for money. Now a worde or two, out of the fathers and counſelles, for the ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng of Diſe and Cardes.<note place="margin">Tertull.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullyan,</hi> and ſome other auncient writers, haue accounted that, which we call <hi>Alea,</hi> that is Cardes and Diſe, and other plaies of lot, and chaunce, ſynne againſt the holy
<pb facs="tcp:3214:22"/> ghoſt. And though thei ſwarne muche from the truth, in makyng it ſo heinous a ſinne, yet haue thei thereby lefte, a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie vnto the world, of their greate diſlikyng, and vtter diſſallowyng, and condemnyng of the ſame <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. 1. officio. 23. Chriſoſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel. 6. in Mat.</note> condemne all maner of plaies, and therfore theſe of Cardes and Diſe. But if a Caueller would here ſay, why doe you not ſo to? I aunſwere, that for that matter, I haue ſhewed ſome reaſons before, in the thirde Chapter of the treatie. Alledgyng theſe Authors at this tyme, as proofes hereof, that if thei can not allowe any maner of Game, muche leſſe will thei allowe, vnlawfull and euill Games. <hi>Ciprian,</hi> in a booke whiche he did write againſt theſe plaies, affirmeth, that thei are the Deuilles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, which he found out and forged, to haue the Idols &amp; Idolatrie, in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vſe and commendation amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and therefore he condemneth it. And no doubt vpon very good ground. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inuention of the Deuill is accurſed, and ought not either to be in vſe or eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:3214:23"/> emongſt thoſe which be Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. <hi>Bernard</hi> exhorteth certain ſouldiars that were at Ieruſalem, to whom he did write, to be at vtter defiaunce with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and Diſe. <hi>Nicholaus de Lyra,</hi> in a little booke of his named <hi>Praeceptorium</hi> putteth doune nine reaſons, for euery of whiche, theſe kindes of Plaies ought to be prohibited amongſt Chriſtians, and exiled from the congregation of God. I will not put doune the wordes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he vſeth, becauſe thei be ſomewhat long. It is enough to note his conſent with the reſt, in diſliking of theſe wicked and vnlawfull exerciſes.<note place="margin">Caluin. epla. 374.</note> 
                  <hi>Maiſter Caluin</hi> a ſingular inſtrument of the Churche of God, writeth thus. There are other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions whiche ſhoote at this marke. For Diſe and Cardes (as thei call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) howſoeuer thei ſemed not to appertaine to ſuperſtition, yet were thei the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of other vices, and brought in euery where, muche hurte and miſchiefe. And as touchyng theſe plaies, we would not ſo muche condemne them, if men in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of them would weigh what were
<pb facs="tcp:3214:23"/> lawfull. But where I praie you ſhall a man finde, that ſobernes and moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Firſte, there is no other thyng any where, by whiche men are ſo hindered, euen as it were by birdlime, ſo that it oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth all their wittes and ſenſes, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then if thei were bewitched.</p>
               <p>But as thei which are accuſtomed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, cannot ſo eaſely bid them farewel: ſo he which hath a little withdrawen his foote, ſhall quickly and eaſely loth them all. Now, thei which giue ouer them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to ſuch thinges, and goe on forward in that madneſſe, whatſoeuer thei be, fall into many miſeries and greifes. It is well enough knowne, that Games can not paſſe without blaſphemies, deceites, wrath, braulyng, and other ſuche like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences. How many good houſes, haue by the ſame, bin as it were cut vp and rooted out? For no man keepeth a meaſure, but either he doeth quickly, or as it were at once waſte hym ſelf, or by little and little, conſume that whiche he hath. Chiefly where queſtion is of gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, it can hardly be, but that by ſome
<pb facs="tcp:3214:24"/> one meane or other, God hymſelf ſhould he offended. Wherefore it is very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, to be as muche as maie free from theſe Games: but beſt of all it is, wholie and altogether to abſtaine from them. And for the more plaine proofe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of theſe wordes of <hi>Maiſter Caluin,</hi> concernyng the diſtruction and ouerthrowe of families and houſholdes, I dare aduouche, and that vpon credite of good Hiſtoriographers, that it hath vndoen ſondrie Kynges of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and as it were ſubdued their eſtate. And one <hi>Bohemus</hi> writing of the maners,<note place="margin">Bohem. lib. 3. de moribus legibus. &amp;c.</note> lawes and of Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, ſheweth that the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes haue bin ſo muche giuen to this plaie, that when thei haue loſt al that thei had, thei would at the laſt caſt, plaie for their libertie. <hi>Peter Martir</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries vpon the booke of Iudges, bothe ſheweth his iudgement touchyng plaies, and alſo aunſwereth an obiection or two, that the vpholders and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſame, haue vſually in their mouthes. His wordes are theſe. And if there were nothyng els, to feare vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie
<pb facs="tcp:3214:24"/> from plaies: Let vs for Gods ſake weigh this, how greate the penurie of tyme is. The lawe of God requireth ſo many dueties, that not our whole life is able to performe them: and yet ſhall we beſtowe tyme in Plaies? We are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſufficiently ſicke with couetouſnes of money, with ambition to ouercome and excell other. Why doe we ſtirre vp theſe diſeaſes with Plaies? But thou wilt ſaie, theſe thinges are neuer ſtirred vp in me: but now thou muſt remember that thei maie eaſely be ſtirred vp. And we muſt ſee not onely to our ſelues, but that wee bryng no other alſo, vnto the ſame diſeaſe. Theſe thinges are ſpoken of the honeſt kinde of plaies. If ſo bee there be any whiche doe plaie, beyng in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed with couetouſneſſe, let theſe men knowe, that thei rather like euill Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes trafficke, then plaie. For they ſeeke no other thyng, but filthie gaine. Neither ſeeke thei pleaſure, whiche in honeſt plaies is the chiefeſt, but thei ſeke their owne thynges, and that by filthie meanes. And when thei whiche delight
<pb facs="tcp:3214:25"/> immoderately in plaies doe ſaie. There muſt be ſome pleaſure in the life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we maie bee recreated, there requeſt is to be graunted: but in the meane tyme thei muſt be admoniſhed, that there are other pleaſures more honeſte. <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> the fifte Chapter ſaieth.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Speake vnto your ſelues in Pſalmes, Hymnes, and ſpirituall ſonges, ſingyng and makyng melodie in your hartes.</hi> And the ſame writeth he vnto the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colloſ. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> in <hi>Apologetico</hi> ſaith, that Chriſtians vſed to aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to their moderate Suppers, and when thei were refreſhed with meate, thei ſang diuine praiſes, or recited ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng out of the holy Scriptures, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokyng one an other by them. And by this meanes thei returned ſober home. And <hi>Maiſter Dearyng</hi> our owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie man, and a deare Sainct of God, hath theſe wordes. Shall we thinke we haue the ſpirite of God, or any portion in Ieſus Chriſte, who in his euerlaſtyng continuaunce, cannot finde ſuche plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as in a viſare of a vaine life, that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely
<pb facs="tcp:3214:25"/> appeareth, and is no more? Who in the glorie of his preſence,<note place="margin">In cap. 1. ad Hebri. lect. 5.</note> and Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of his Father, can ſee no ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light as in Cardyng, Diſyng, Daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, and ſuche like workes of reproche and ſhame and horrible confuſion.</p>
               <p>In the Canons of the Apoſtles (whiche are ſo called, and counted verie auncient) this plaie of Diſe and Cardes is plainlie forbidden, and altogether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected.<note place="margin">Cano. Apoſt. can 41.</note> The woordes there putte doune are theſe. <hi>A Miniſter or Elder, or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, whiche giueth hym ſelf to Diſe, Cardes, and drunkenneſſe, either lette hym ceaſſe there from, or be depoſed.</hi> The ſixte Counſell of Conſtantinople,<note place="margin">Concilium Conſtant. 6. can. 50. &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur. tom. 20. concil. pag. 148.</note> hath theſe woordes. <hi>Wee decree that no manne, whether he bee Clarke or Laie manne, from this tyme forward plaie at Diſe or Cardes.</hi> Now if any manne ſhall from this tyme forward attempte to doe it, if he bee a Clergie manne (as wee vſe to call hym commonlie, whiche is of the Miniſterie) let hym bee depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if he bee a Laie manne, let hym bee excommunicate. And in the Counſell of
<pb facs="tcp:3214:26"/> 
                  <hi>Eliberis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Con. Eliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum can. 79. &amp; habetur tom. 10. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. pag. 367.</note> it is thus decreed. <hi>If any faithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manne plaie at Diſe or Cardes, let it pleaſe hym to abſtaine: and if he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende and leaue of, he maie after a ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſpace, bee receiued to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> Yea, and twoo godlie Synodes, helde not many yeres ſince in Fraunce, the one at Rochel, the other at Nimaur, by the Paſtours, Elders, and Deacons of the reformed Churches of that kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, haue with a full and plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, vtterlie forbidden theſe vnlawfull Games. I thinke theſe teſtimonies and witneſſes are ſufficient.</p>
               <p>See how ſome altogether condemne it, and other calleth it, the inuention of the Deuill: an other ſaieth, it is beſte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to abſtaine from them. The Councelles ſaie, the Clarke ſhalbee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued if he vſe it, and the Laye manne Excommunicated, and not receiued to the Communion, in a yeres ſpace after. One would thinke that theſe thynges were ſufficient enough, to diſcourage menne from theſe vaine and idle exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but yet for promiſe ſake, I wil adde
<pb facs="tcp:3214:26"/> ſomewhat more, taken out of the Ciuill and Canon Lawe, and out of the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimes them ſelues againſt theſe Plaies, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſhall ſee in al ages, though neuer ſo corrupte, and emongeſt all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, though neuer ſo ill and wicked, theſe deteſtable Plaies of Cardes and Diſe, to haue been reiected and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thei maie learne to walke in better order, and perfectlie to forſake their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vanitie and ſynne.</p>
               <p>There is an old Lawe of the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and is yet at this daie,<note place="margin">In ff. de Alea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur. lib. 1. Pandec. tit. 5.</note> founde in the digeſtes, whiche ſaieth thus. <hi>If any one haue beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, with whom he plaied at Cardes or at Diſe, or haue doen hym any wrong: or if duryng the tyme that an other plaied with hym, ſome thyng hath been taken from him, or his houſe robbed, I will dooe no Iuſtice to hym ſaith the Pretor. If any haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained, or perſwaded an other to plaie, I will puniſhe hym accordyng, as the matter requireth, ſo that he ſhalbe caſt, either into the quarries to digge ſtones, or els into the common priſons.</hi> Hence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3214:27"/> the vnlawfulneſſe of theſe Plaies, becauſe the Magiſtrate, will neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde hym the money, whiche hath wonne it, nor puniſhe the wrong that one of them doeth to an other, when thei plaie at theſe wicked Games. The grounde and occaſion of whiche Lawe, I take it to be this, that the Magiſtrate was inforced to vſe this hard extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of omittyng of adminiſtration of Iuſtice, and giuyng libertie to beate one an other, and to fight one with an other, becauſe that by other meanes, the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and vnbrideled nature of manne, could not bee tamed or ſubdued. To this adde the Decree of the godlie Emperor <hi>Iuſtinian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cod Iuſtin. tit 43. lib. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Hauyng regard</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>to our Subiectes wealth, we by this lawe, prohibite in all places, and to all ſortes of people, to plaie either in common houſes, or priuate houſes</hi> (it is as much as if he ſhould ſaie, either in Innes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes, Alehouſes, or in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (at the plaies of Cardes and of Diſe, neither ſo muche as to be looker on. And by the ſame Lawe he chargeth Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes<note place="margin">A little after.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3214:27"/> and Paſtours, diligentlie to take heede therevnto, and enioyneth them, that for the reformation of this euill, thei vſe and imploye the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, of the Iudges and Gouernours of their Prouinces, as is ſpecified in <hi>Autent de Sacroſan. Epiſc. §. Interdici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Where alſo he doeth prohibite by name, that no Biſhop, Elder, or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, ſhould either plaie them ſelues, or looke vpon them that plaie.</p>
               <p>By the Lawes and Statutes of that godlie citie <hi>Geneua,</hi> the verie makyng of Cardes and Diſe,<note place="margin">The lawes of Geneua. fol. 70. pag. 1. lin. 12. &amp; fol. 80. pag. 1. lin. 22.</note> and ſuche other thynges, is expreſſelie forbidden vppon paine to forfeite, not only the thinges ſo made, but alſo three ſcore Shillynges. The ground of whiche Lawe I take to bee this, that the cauſe beeyng taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, the effecte alſo is remoued and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaie. And therefore thei haue very godlilie, and Chriſtianlie prohibited the makyng of theſe thynges, followyng no doubt therein, the verie example and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of the Lorde, who becauſe he would haue his people to abſtaine from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:28"/> doeth forbidde them the makyng of all maner of Idolles.<note place="margin">Exodus. 20.4.</note> Yea the Canon Lawe, (whiche came in when the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Churche, were marueilouſly corrupted, hath this plaie in no leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation. <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 35. <hi>cap. Epiſcopi.</hi> Either let them ceaſſe to plaie, or lette them bee condemned. And <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Decretal. cap. Chroni.</hi> Lette theim not plaie at Diſe or Tables, neither lette theim bee preſent at ſuche plaies. Yea, but thei will ſaie, theſe Lawes haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte to Eccleſiaſticall perſones. That is true. But what then? Therefore it bindeth not vs. I deny the conſequent. For <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epiſtles to <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Timoth. 3.2. &amp;c. Titus. 1.6.</note> rehearſyng what qualities ought to bee in a Biſhoppe or Paſtour of the Churche, declareth what good thinges are to be required of the churche Miniſter, as, that he muſte bee vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable, the houſbande of one wife, ſober, modeſt, not giuen to filthie lucre, not coueteous, &amp;c. Shall wee therefore ſaie, that none of theſe thinges, ought to bee in Chriſtians. If wee ſhould ſo ſaie,
<pb facs="tcp:3214:28"/> the woorde of GOD would preſently ſtoppe our mouthes, whiche bothe in the old and newe Teſtament requireth both theſe, and many other dueties of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Charitie, to bee in them that profeſſe Chriſtes name.</p>
               <p>There bee ſome thynges that bee ſo tied to the perſones of Miniſters, that in an ordinarie ſtate of the Churche, thei ought not to bee ſeparated from theim, of whiche ſorte, I take to bee preachyng of the woorde, Miniſteryng of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, conceiuyng praiers in the Congregation, &amp;c. Others there are,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 5.3.</note> whiche though thei bee required in the firſt place of the Miniſter, becauſe he is to make hym ſelf an example and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of holineſſe of life to his flocke, yet thei doe alſo belong, as it were in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde place, to the Churche and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of GOD, in as muche as the Lorde doeth in his holie worde, require of all his children, a ſober, honeſt, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie life. And in this reſpecte, I thinke that the Lawes prohibityng theſe plaies in the Miniſters and Paſtours, dooeth
<pb facs="tcp:3214:29"/> alſo diſallowe and diſlike of the ſame, in their flockes and Congregation. Let vs come now to ſhewe the iudgement, that the Heathen menne haue had of this matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">M.T.C. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Catilin.</note>
                  <hi>Tullie,</hi> in an oration he made againſt <hi>Catalina,</hi> vpbradeth hym and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions after this maner. <hi>In thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies were conuerſaunt, all that were Diſers and Carders, all that were adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, all that were impure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamefaſte, impudent and ſhameleſſe menne.</hi> See with what a route, as O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xen in one yoke, and vices as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably ioyned together, he ioyneth men giuen ouer to theſe plaies of Diſe and Cardes. And in another Oration, whiche he made before all the Senate, againſte <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M.T.C. Philip 2.</note> he caſteth hym in the teeth with this, as one of the moſte greeuous crimes, which he could laie againſt him, becauſe he vſed to plaie at that Game, whiche the Latiniſtes call <hi>Alia,</hi> that is to ſaie, according to our time, at the plaie of Cardes and of Diſe and other ſuche Games of lotte and of
<pb facs="tcp:3214:29"/> chaunce, chargyng hym, that his houſe was filled with Carders and Diſers, and druncken perſones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> notwithſtandyng,<note place="margin">Suetonius in vita. Auguſti cap. 71.</note> that he had many excellent and greate vertues, yet the verie brute whiche did runne emongeſt the people, ſaiyng that he plaied at ſuche plaies, was turned to his greate diſpraiſe, and made hym to hee counted diſſolute.</p>
               <p>It is reported of <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> Emperour alſo of Rome,<note place="margin">Idem in vita Claudij.</note> that by many vices, emongſt whiche his plaiyng at Cardes, and Diſe is rehearſed, he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed hym ſelf to bee a foole, and an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt manne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gobilon</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſent to <hi>Corinth,</hi> to make truce with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> returned verie quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, without concludyng any thing with them, becauſe he ſawe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plaie at ſuche plaies, ſaiyng: that it was not meete or ſeemelie, for the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> to make league, or haue any acquaintance, with ſuche diſſolute and rude people, and of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no account was to be made.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3214:30"/>
               <p>The Kyng of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſent to <hi>Demetrius</hi> Kyng of <hi>Aſia,</hi> Diſe of gold, thereby to reproche hym, of follie, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and idleneſſe. Little children knew this ſaiyng of <hi>Cato</hi> verie well, and haue it written: <hi>Trocho lude, alias fuge.</hi> Play with Toppe; but flee from Diſe and Cardes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aſconius pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianus in 2. lib. diuinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. M.T.C.</note>
                  <hi>Aſconius Pedianus</hi> writeth, that ſuche plaies were at Rome in old tyme condemned, to forfeite fower tymes as muche, as that whiche thei had plaied for. <hi>Horace</hi> in one verſe pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſetteth out the inconuenience of whoredome, and plaiyng at Diſe &amp; Cardes, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng: <hi>Qnem damnoſa Venus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horatius in epiſtolis.</note> 
                  <hi>quem praecipe alea nudat.</hi> That is to ſaie: who harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and damnable whoredome, together with the ouer raſhe plaie of Diſe and Cardes, doe ſpoile and make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iuuenal. Satyr 14.</note>And <hi>Iuuenal,</hi> putteth it emong the vices, whiche moſte eaſelie corrupte all the familie, and ſhewe moſte wicked example, in a houſe, whiche ſhould bee well ruled. His woordes in effecte are theſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3214:30"/>
                  <l>When that the father doeth beginne,</l>
                  <l>with Cardes and Diſe to plaie,</l>
                  <l>In preſence of his children yong,</l>
                  <l>to paſſe the tyme awaie.</l>
                  <l>His child doeth then take them in hande</l>
                  <l>in pleaſure ſpendyng tyme:</l>
                  <l>And ſo at length proceedes to vſe,</l>
                  <l>his fooliſhe fathers coyne.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I could here alledge more, but I take theſe teſtimonies and examples to bee ſufficient, for the full performaunce and accompliſhement, of that whiche I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. Out of whiche we maie gather, that all menne, good and badde, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or not Chriſtians, haue as it wer with one common voice, ſhewed bothe their diſlikyng of the ſame, and giuen reaſons, why other ſhould abſtain there from. So that now, there ſeemeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng to remaine, but the laſte parte of this treatie, that is: to aunſwere ſuche mennes obiections, as maintaine theſe plaies, whiche I will dooe, in as fewe woordes, and as plainlie as I can. In deede I muſte confeſſe, that I am not
<pb facs="tcp:3214:31"/> ſkilfull in their obiections, and therefore ſhall neither putte doune, nor aunſwere all, that thei will, or can bryng for them ſelues. How beit, here I proteſt, that ſo many as I can call to remembraunce, I will plainlie expreſſe, as hauyng had them of other, rather then framyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſelf, and alſo promiſe, that if any pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone of theſe corruptions, ſhall alledge any more, I will be readie to deale with hym, either by freendlie conference, or publike writyng, let hym take whether waie, ſhalbe beſt likyng to hym ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶The vij. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, thei obiect a place of Scripture or twoo. One out of the thirde Chapter of the booke of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, whereas it is ſaied, that there is a time to euery purpoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heauen.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 3.1.</note> Whereupon thei inforce, that there is a tyme to plaie at Cardes and Diſe, and other vnlawfull Games. To this I aunſwere, firſt that thei make
<pb facs="tcp:3214:31"/> an euill concluſion, out of thoſe generall termes of the holy ghoſte, whoſe mynde is not in that place, to allot a tyme to the doynges of thinges vnlawfull (of which ſorte wee haue before proued this kinde of Gamyng to be) for if that were true, why ſhould ther not be a tyme of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of drunckenneſſe, of vſurie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuche like vices: but to ſet out vnto vs, that there is nothyng in the worlde perpetuall, and that therefore,<note place="margin">1. Corin. 7.31.</note> we ſhould vſe the worlde, as though we vſed it not, becauſe the faſhion of this worlde, and the glorie thereof, goeth awaie as Clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the winde. Thei alledge an other place out of the ſeuenth Chapter of the ſame booke.<note place="margin">Eccleſia. 7.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee not thou iuſte ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche, neither make thy ſelf ouerwiſe.</hi> For that is to bryng in (ſaie thei) ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and to take awaie Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. Touchyng Chriſtian libertie, I haue ſpoken ſomewhat before, ſo that I neede not to repeate that in this place. Onely we are to conſider of the place al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and to ſee, whether ſuperſtition will inſue, vpon the takyng awaie of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful
<pb facs="tcp:3214:32"/> games from among Chriſtians. In deede I am not ignoraunt, how that mans nature is prone to ſuperſtition, neuer keepyng a meane, and therefore it maie be, that if theſe men ſhould not haue that, whiche thei deſire and wiſhe, thei would fall into an other extremitie as ill, as vnlawfull games. But you ſee, that all plaie and recreation, is not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, but onely thoſe whiche fight ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt Goddes worde, and haue bin with ſuche a generall conſent, diſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and diſallowed. So that, the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of fallyng into ſuperſtition and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, is taken awaie, in as muche, as an honeſt and orderly refreſhing of wearied myndes, is left vnto Chriſtians. But lette vs examine the place it ſelf, and ſee how well theſe men applie Scriptures. A wonderfull thyng it is, then mannes harte ſhould bee ſo euill, to applie that, whiche God hath reueiled in his worde, for the beating doune of the pride of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature, and ſynne in him, to a leuſeneſſe and libertie, if not to all ſynne, yet to a greate number of miſchiefes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes.
<pb facs="tcp:3214:32"/> The mynde of the holy Ghoſt in that place, is to teache vs,<note place="margin">1. Corin. 3.5.</note> not to think muche of any thyng, which is in vs. For what haue we, that wee haue not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? And if we haue receiued it, why re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce we,<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 64.6.</note> as though we had not receiued it? Neither to be puffed vp, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our owne rightouſneſſe, for all our rightouſneſſe before God, is as filthie cloutes. And yet theſe men dare applie it, to giue thereby libertie vnto the fleſhe, and the reines to muche licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe, wheras we are taught by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.22.</note> to abſteine not onely from that whiche is euill in it ſelf, but alſo from all appearaunce of euill. Now theſe plaies of Cardes and Diſe, and ſuch other like, whiche wee comprehende vnder the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of plaies, of lot, chaunce, or hazard, are (as we haue ſhewed before) not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appearyng to be euill, but be in deede euill and vnlawfull. Wherefore if the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie ſhould iudge, that this is ouer greate ſeueritie and rigor, to take away from Chriſtians, the vſe of theſe vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Gaines (whiche yet in deede is not
<pb facs="tcp:3214:33"/> true, becauſe there is none that forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them honeſtly, and moderately, to plaie and refreſhe them ſelues, at all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfull plaies, which maie ſerue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the recreation and ſolace of the ſpirite, or for healthfull, and moderate exerciſe of the bodie) then I might moſt truely ſaie and affirme, that this ſhould argue, to muche diſſoluteneſſe amongſt men, and diſobedience againſte God, to approue and permit them.<note place="margin">Chriſoſtome. homel. 1. a.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> hath a notable ſaiyng, in the firſte Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or Homelie that he made, touching the leuſnes and diſſolutions of his time, aunſwearyng as it ſhould ſeeme to the like obiection. When men ſaieth he cut of from the life of the faithfull, the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which are therein ſuperfluous, they bryng them not to ouer greate auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of life, but to ſuche a conuerſation, as thei ſhould walke in.<note place="margin">Gregor. in Reg.</note> And <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith he that amendeth not the thinges, which ſhould bee cutte of, committeth the ſelf ſame thinges, and he hath the faulte of a doer laide vpon hym, who neglecteth to amende that, whiche he maie and ought
<pb facs="tcp:3214:33"/> to amende.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, thei obiecte, that ſeeyng thei can plaie at theſe Games, without othes, anger, coueteouſneſſe, contention brawlynges, and ſuche other like incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences, thei maie lawfully vſe the ſame: I aunſwere to this twoo maner of waies. Firſte, that either verie hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or not all, thei ſhalbée able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to any godlie manne, that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth (by what meanes ſoeuer it bee, it ſkilleth not, whether it bee, by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in hym ſelfe, or by the truthe of Gods woorde) the euill and corruption of mannes harte, the truthe of this their aſſertion. For I ſuppoſe that, there is not one whiche vſeth theſe Games, though he plaie for neuer ſo little, muche more if he plaie for a greate wager or ſumme, but he hath in hym a greedie deſire to winne. Whiche verie deſire is euill and naught, becauſe it coueteth that, whiche is an other mannes. And no doubte of it, as there is in theim, this deſire to haue an other mannes: ſo there is lothſomneſſe and vnwillyngneſſe, to
<pb facs="tcp:3214:34"/> forgoe their owne. Whiche when thei haue loſte, though many tymes thei co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, with a faire countenaunce, and abſtaine from outwarde anger, yet as Salomon ſaieth,<note place="margin">Prouer. 14 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Euen in laughyng the harte is ſorowfull, and the ende of that mirthe is heauineſſe.</hi> For thei frette in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie, and it gréeueth theim at the harte, that thei are defeated of that hope, whiche thei had to winne an other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and haue loſte their owne. And tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the truthe of theſe thinges, I will aſke no better Iudges or witneſſes, then the conſciences and mouthes of menne them ſelues, moſte giuen to this plaie, if thei will freelie and truelie, with their tongues confeſſe, that whiche by daiely experience, thei feele in their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
               <p>Secondlie I ſaie, that though thei could plaie without all theſe perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (whiche thyng I can hardelie bee brought to yeeld vnto) yet maie not thei lawfullie plaie at theſe Games, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſſe of whiche, I haue before ſhewed. Lette theim rather giue theim
<pb facs="tcp:3214:34"/> ſelues to vſe ſuche lawfull and honeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, as thei maie with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and not runne headlonglie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe manifolde miſchéefes: From the leaſte of whiche, euery one of vs ought (ſo farre forthe as GOD ſhall make vs able) to keepe our ſelues frée and cleane. But thei ſaie againe, wee cannot ſo well refreſhe our ſelues with any kinde of Game or Plaie, as with Cardes and Diſe. Nowe ſurelie I thinke thei ſaie true, and that which thei alledge, as a reaſon for the vſe of theim, I will take for a reaſon againſte theim. For this, to witte that wee take ſuche greate pleaſure in theim, not onelie ought to make them ſuſpected vnto vs, but argueth alſo the vnlawfulneſſe of them. For who knoweth not the Poets ſaiyng to bee true. <hi>Ruimus per vetitum nefas.</hi> Wée runne headlonglie into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefes forbidden vs.</p>
               <p>And why I praie you, ſhould there not be as greate recreation, in the game of the Cheſtes, the Philoſophers game, and ſuche like, whiche in all mens Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes
<pb facs="tcp:3214:35"/> are counted lawfull, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Cardes and Diſe, and ſuche other, whiche are condemned, with ſo generall a conſent, as is before declared. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of this kinde of plaie, are wonte further to obiecte, what if wée will ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe our money? Are wée not Lordes of our owne thinges? We doe no wrong to our neighbour. Wee take not awaie other mennes goodes. Theſe thynges haue thei continuallie in their mouthes. But thei ought to vnderſtande, that it is their duetie, to vſe your owne thinges well, in performyng whereof if thei be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſlacke, then let them knowe, that both<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thei ſhall render an accounte, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beſtowyng and abuſyng of Gods goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giftes, of whiche the Lorde hath made theim Stewardes for a tyme, and alſo that it is the duetie of the Magiſtrate, to ſee too and redreſſe that abuſe. Beſides thei are deepely to conſider, that GOD giueth theim money, that thereby they might haue meanes, to prouide for their families, and to nouriſhe theim, and to helpe the poore, and not to caſte theim to
<pb facs="tcp:3214:35"/> chaunce, and to put them to the ſlipper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Fortune. Further, all, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie Chriſtians, beyng Gods children ought to repreſent the Image of God, (who gouerneth and ruleth all thynges with reaſon) as in other thynges, ſo in this, that with godlie conſcience, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and foreſight, thei dooe ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as thei ought to dooe. Againe, who can iudge otherwiſe, then that thus to conſume money, as not to be a Lorde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his owne thynges, but a tyraunt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as if a Kyng, becauſe he hath the rule and aucthoritie ouer his Subiectes, ſhould not onely ſpoyle theim of their goodes, but of their life alſo, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good reaſon or lawfull cauſe. Adde alſo herevnto, that if any thyng bée got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by theſe meanes, the ſame is called of many, filthie gaine. And if it were not of it ſelf, filthie gaine, but onely got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by euill name and reporte (whiche I thinke fewe will denie, yet would the Poet <hi>Minus</hi> tell vs, that <hi>Damnum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellandumeſt cum mala fama, lucrum,</hi> that is to ſaie:
<q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3214:36"/>
                     <l>That gaine whiche is gotten,</l>
                     <l>with an euill name:</l>
                     <l>Is to be called loſſe to hym,</l>
                     <l>whiche getteth the ſame.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore we ſhould auoyde it. Neither is it of any force, whiche ſome ſaie. Theſe exerciſes are moſte fit for the Winter, when the daies are foule, and the nightes long. For the fouleneſſe of the weather and the length of the night, cannot alter the nature of the thyng, as of vnlawfull to make it lawfull. If they wil replie thus. If we may not vſe theſe, wee knowe not how to ſpende the tyme. To this I aunſwere, that there are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte exerciſes of recreation, whiche a Chriſtian maie well and lawfully vſe. Yea ſaie thei, but wee can not plaie at them, and theſe wee haue learned alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Hereto I ſaie, firſt that it is and hath bin in them. <hi>Turpe diſcere dediſcenda,</hi> a filthie thyng to learne thynges, whiche afterwardes muſte bee forgotten. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie, that thei ought to forget theſe, and if that by ſingyng of Pſalmes, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb facs="tcp:3214:36"/> of the Scriptures, and other good bookes, and ſuche like heauenly exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thei cannot recreate them ſelues, then to vſe ſuch lawfull and Godly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe as becommeth Chriſtians, and not to giue them ſelues ouer, to theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked plaies of chaunce or hazarde. An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obiection thei make thus. We are Gentlemen, and men of good counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce in the common wealth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes haue reſorte bothe of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualles, and ſuperiors to vs, who would gladly plaie at ſuche Games. Will you haue vs to bee ſo diſcourteous, that we ſhall not keepe them companie. I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that though that, whiche we call curteſie, conſiſteth partely in this, that a man maie plaie and recreate hym ſelfe with others, yet it permitteth vs not, to plaie at deteſtable plaies with them (ſuch as theſe plaies are) but onely allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs to ſporte our ſelues, at honeſte and lawfull plaies, and that in meaſure to, and ſo farre forthe as neede ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. So that if the one be inſtructed, he is not in reſpecte of curteſie, to yeeld to
<pb facs="tcp:3214:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> an vnlawfull thyng, for the others ſake. If neither be inſtructed, then bothe are to knowe, that the vſe and exerciſe of theſe Games, is a thyng vnlawfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be vſed of them.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
